Guide to the Provost Marshal of the 7th Congressional District of New York City Records 1863-1865 MS498
© 2011 New-York Historical Society
Provost Marshal of the 7th Congressional District of New York City Records
1863-1865
MS498
© 2011 New-York Historical Society
2.75 Linear feet (5 boxes, 6 bound volumes)
This collection contains records from the Office of the Provost Marshal, Seventh Congressional District, New York, which oversaw enlistments for the Union Army from the 11th and 17th wards of New York City. Portions of this collection relating to the Civil War have been digitized and are available to on-site researchers and to users affiliated with subscribing institutions via EBSCOhost.
Historical note
On March 3, 1863, Congress passed the first national draft in United States history (although not the first on American soil: the Confederate government instituted the draft for its army almost a year earlier). Passed to provide manpower for the Union Army, which by this time was long on casualties and short on volunteers, the Enrollment Act subjected all men between the ages of 20 and 45 to the draft.
The legislation also created the administrative machinery necessary to implement the Federal draft. A new Provost Marshal General's Office was added to the War Department, and charged with overall administration of conscription. The country was divided into enrolling districts along the lines of congressional districts. Each district was headed by a provost marshal who was responsible for registering and calling up draftees. The provost marshals also had broad authority to arrest and detain all persons resisting the draft or discouraging enlistments.
The number of men called for by the President was apportioned by district, establishing for each district a quota of men to enroll. Enrolling officers had the unenviable task of going door-to-door to identify all men eligible for service. After this laborious process, names were drawn at a public lottery to determine who would be called to service. If enough men volunteered to fill the quota in a particular district, the draft would not apply there.
The provost marshal also determined who was eligible for the various draft exemptions provided under the Act, such as mental and physical disability. More controversially, draftees who had the means could escape service by paying a $300 exemption fee or providing a substitute. Nowhere were these provisions resented more than in the poor neighborhoods of New York City, which erupted in riots on July 13, 1863, after the names of the first draftees were drawn. As a result, the first draft in the 7th Congressional District of New York City, originally ordered for July 14, 1863, did not take place until August 25, 1863.
Arrangement note
This collection has been organized into the following two series:
Series I: Loose documents
Series II: Bound volumes
Documents are arranged by type, and chronologically within each category, where possible.
Conditions Governing Access
Open to qualified researchers.
Portions of the collection that have been microfilmed will be brought to the researcher in that format and can be made available by Interlibrary loan. Researchers on site may print out unlimited copies from microfilm reader-printer machines at per-exposure rates. See guidelines in Reading Room for details.
Photocopying undertaken by staff only. Limited to twenty exposures of stable, unbound material per day. (Researchers may not accrue unused copy amounts from previous days.)
Items that include presidential signatures will be presented to researchers in duplicate form.
Scope and Contents
This collection consists of correspondence and other records of Captain Frederick C. Wagner in his capacity as provost marshal of the 7th Congressional District (encompassing the 11th and 17th wards) of New York City. The papers concern the conscription, enrollment and provisioning of Union soldiers, as well as requests for exemptions, substitutes, deserters, and claims against the government for property damage. Portions of this collection relating to the Civil War have been digitized and are available to on-site researchers and to users affiliated with subscribing institutions via EBSCOhost.
The collection has been organized into two series. Series I, Loose papers, includes correspondence, receipts, contracts, certificates and other official papers sent to or issued by Captain Frederick C. Wagner; circulars from the Office of the Acting Assistant Provost Marshal General at Albany; receipts for clothing issues; returns of public property; requisitions; descriptive lists and muster rolls; and receipts from a campaign to raise recruitment funds in the 17th ward. Also included is Wagner's summary report of the business transacted by his office during the Civil War, which gives a useful overview of office operations.
Series II includes six bound volumes. Two volumes contain enrollment lists of substitutes and volunteers. Entries for volunteers include descriptive information such as the enrollee's age, height, build, complexion, place of birth, occupation, and family. A third volume records a list of persons arrested for desertion from New York regiments, and provides personal descriptions of each man arrested, the date and place of enlistment, desertion, and arrest; name of the person responsible for the arrest; and subsequent fate of the individual following his arrest. The fourth volume contains a record of clothing and eating utensils distributed to volunteers and substitutes.
Series II also includes a notebook, probably kept by Frederick C. Wagner, listing men in the 11th and 17th wards who claimed exemption, had provided substitutes, or were already enrolled as volunteers or substitutes. The notes give names and addresses of the men, some personal information about them, and notes on the money paid to recruits and men enlisted as substitutes. A final volume contains the Circulars issued by the Acting Assistant Provost Marshal General of the Southern Division of New York.
- Series I: Loose documents
  - Summary report of business transacted during Civil War, 1865 June (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence and receipts, 1862 September - 1863 September (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence and receipts, 1863 October - December (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence and receipts, 1864 January - March (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence and receipts, 1864 April - June (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence and receipts, 1864 July - September (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence and receipts, 1864 October - December (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence and receipts, 1865 January - March (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence and receipts, 1865 April - June (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence and receipts, 1865 July - December, undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Forms extending furlough in order to procure a substitute, 1863 September - October (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Circulars, 1863 May - December (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Circulars, 1864 January - June (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Circulars, 1864 July - November (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Circulars, 1864 December - 1865 February (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Circulars, 1865 March - October (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Receipts for clothing issues (originals), 1863 September (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Receipts for clothing issues (duplicates), 1863 September (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Receipts for clothing issues (originals), 1863 October (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Receipts for clothing issues (duplicates), 1863 October (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Receipts for clothing issues, 1863 November (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Receipts for clothing issues, 1863 November (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Receipts for clothing issues, 1863 December (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Receipts for clothing issues, 1864 January (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Receipts for clothing issues, 1864 February (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Receipts for clothing issues, 1864 March (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Receipts for clothing issues, 1864 April - May (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Receipts for clothing issues, 1864 June - July (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Receipts for clothing issues, 1864 August - September (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Receipts for clothing issues, 1864 October - December (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Receipts for clothing issues, 1865 January (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Receipts for clothing issues, 1865 February (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Receipts for clothing issues, 1865 March (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Receipts for clothing issues, 1865 April (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Requisitions for rations, 1864 August - 1865 December (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Requisitions for fuel, 1864 September - 1865 December (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Requisitions for straw, 1864 September - 1865 December (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Return of Public Property forms, 1864 September - 1865 October (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Property invoices and auction lists, 1865 May - December (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Descriptive lists and muster rolls, 1864 October - December, undated (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Receipts for campaign to raise recruitment funds for 17th Ward, 1864 March - May (Box 6, Folder 7)
- Series II: Bound volumes
  - Enrollment lists, 1863 September 5 - 1864 May 27 (Volume BV Provost Marshal 7th District)
  - Enrollment lists, 1864 July 12 - 1865 April 13 (Volume BV Provost Marshal 7th District)
  - List of deserters, 1863 June 2 - 1865 May 2 (Volume BV Provost Marshal 7th District)
  - Clothing accounts, 1863 September 4 - 1865 April 12 (Volume BV Provost Marshal 7th District)
  - Notebook of enrolling officer, circa 1863-1865 (Volume BV War of 1861-1865, New York Recruits)
  - Circulars, Office of the Acting Assistant Provost Marshal, Southern District of New York, 1863 November 25 - 1865 May 10 (Volume F126 UB834.N5 U82 1863)